Victoria Wood: Hi, Bert!
Tanner, Bertrand: Hi, Victoria, how are you doing?
Victoria Wood: I'm doing well, how are you?
Tanner, Bertrand: I'm doing alright. You had to make some announcements before we got going, but other than that, I think everything is ready to go.
Victoria Wood: Cool, yep, sounds good.
Tanner, Bertrand: Okay, I'll be right back.
Victoria Wood: How was your, your boating trip earlier this summer?
Tanner, Bertrand: Oh, it's good. And, A nice trip, yeah.
Victoria Wood: It was rafting, like you were doing?
Tanner, Bertrand: Yeah, we were raft in the Yellowstone River. It was more of just a float trip, it wasn't very many rapids.
Victoria Wood: Hmm. Well, sounds great.
Tanner, Bertrand: Good.
Victoria Wood: Beautiful.
Tanner, Bertrand: Oh, that's good.
Tanner, Bertrand: Thanks for asking. How are you?
Victoria Wood: Pretty good.
Tanner, Bertrand: Good.
Victoria Wood: Yeah.
Tanner, Bertrand: I've only been to a couple of these… events this summer.
Tanner, Bertrand: I saw that there's some groups that are, like.
Tanner, Bertrand: Doing watch parties, and then there are some other groups that are… just individual.
Victoria Wood: Yes.
Victoria Wood: Yeah, so we have some of our, like, local teams all just have, like, a conference room.
Victoria Wood: And join in together for that.
Victoria Wood: So if you plan to do breakout rooms, we normally just put the watch parties into, like, their own breakout room.
Tanner, Bertrand: Okay.
Victoria Wood: I'm gonna give people just, like, another minute or so to trickle in, and then I'll just make some quick announcements, and then I'll hand it over to you, okay?
Tanner, Bertrand: call it.
Victoria Wood: Alright… I think we're kind of reaching the amount that we normally get here,
Victoria Wood: I just wanted to welcome everybody, and then I know I sent out, a really long email yesterday about Capstone Symposium, so I just wanted to,
Victoria Wood: just verbally announce that as well. We've released the, tentative program, detailed program for Capstone Symposium, which will be September 10th through 12th in Irvine.
Victoria Wood: So it's…
Victoria Wood: since it's hybrid, we have it in the mornings at Pacific time through the early afternoons to allow for Eastern Time Zone participants to join in. But please do, check that schedule. I need each of the summer teams to have one representative that goes into that schedule and indicates that your team can actually make it at that time.
Victoria Wood: please do be generous with your… or flexible with your scheduling there, because it's very hard to juggle all the 25 teams and everything, so I would appreciate that. Every individual that plans on attending, either virtually or in person, please also complete the RSVP that I sent out in that same email.
Victoria Wood: Just so that we can plan breakout rooms and social activities and,
Victoria Wood: And, food and stuff. It's more important that you RSVP if you're attending in person, but it's helpful to know who's attending virtually as well.
Victoria Wood: And I just wanted to give a quick chance if anybody has any pressing questions about all that information, otherwise you can just message me.
Victoria Wood: All right. Well, if not, I will go ahead and hand it over to you, Dr. Tanner.
Tanner, Bertrand: Hey everybody, it's good to see you today on…
Tanner, Bertrand: talking a little bit about, muscle mechanics. We're going to be talking about some, cross-bridge cycling and how to measure some
Tanner, Bertrand: Actin and myosin kinetics in terms of attachment rates and detachment rates, and a little bit of system analysis.
Tanner, Bertrand: We'll see how this all gets going with trying to share my screen and making sure that we
Tanner, Bertrand: Can see everything, so…
Tanner, Bertrand: You should be seeing something that is associated with, like, a Google Drive right now?
Tanner, Bertrand: that is associated with, like, the CrossBridge Kinetics Workshop, and I think that Victoria will probably send out
Tanner, Bertrand: information or links to this if you don't already have it. I just wanted to give you a background of some of the stuff we put together here. I've uploaded the PowerPoint, and I've uploaded a PDF of the PowerPoint as well, if that were easier.
Tanner, Bertrand: I've put in,
Tanner, Bertrand: a folder here that has some kind of classic papers that I'll just talk briefly about today, if you wanted to review any of them, or if you had further questions.
Tanner, Bertrand: And then, Maddy Chastain is an undergraduate in my lab, and she helped put together some data fitting examples, which are all MATLAB-based code, and if you look in there, in these data fitting examples, we've got some
Tanner, Bertrand: Human cardiac data, where we did some sinusoidal system analysis, some human cardiac data, where we did
Tanner, Bertrand: Some step analysis, and then we've got some…
Tanner, Bertrand: RAT data, where there's a step analysis for both fast twitch and slow twitch muscle, and, like, within each of these folders.
Tanner, Bertrand: there's this little PowerPoint that says how to use the fitting scripts that Maddy put together that hopefully will help get people started if you wanted to try those.
Tanner, Bertrand: throughout the end of the workshop today, or once I'm done with some of the presentation, I thought there'd be time to either… I can show you how to do these, or Maddie can show them on her screen.
Tanner, Bertrand: But I just wanted to say those are some of the resources we put together for…
Tanner, Bertrand: our discussion today.
Tanner, Bertrand: And then, so, to get the PowerPoint going, do you guys see the PowerPoint now?
Victoria Wood: Yeah.
Tanner, Bertrand: Okay, thank you, that's great. Something's going weird with all of my screens on my computer this morning, so I'm glad it's working out. That's nice to know.
Tanner, Bertrand: And so, here we are going to be talking about the effects of some details in the beginning on muscle length and cross-bridge kinetics, and then, as I mentioned, a little bit of discussion on some of the experimental system analysis to measure the cross-bridge kinetics.
Tanner, Bertrand: And everything I'm going to be talking about today has to do with Either cardiac or skeletal muscle.
Tanner, Bertrand: where we've… Dissected a piece of tissue down to
Tanner, Bertrand: a small piece of tissue de-membranated the tissue, so it doesn't have a cell membrane. So I know a lot of you guys do excitable preparations, or whole muscle preparations that are electrically stimulated, or you stimulate the nerve, or something like that. These are just…
Tanner, Bertrand: Demembranated fibers, so depending on the calcium bath that we switch it to, or the levels of ATP and things like that, that'll change how the skin
Tanner, Bertrand: Fibers contract.
Tanner, Bertrand: So that's a little different than probably most of you are working with. So the outline, I was just going to tell you some of my training background.
Tanner, Bertrand: I wanted to do a brief introduction to make sure we're all on the same page about just the biology. And then I've got one example where I wanted to show you about sinusoidal system analysis and how we've used that to look at some cross-bridge kinetic differences as we change the muscle length.
Tanner, Bertrand: And then I wanted to just do a little bit of a brief history or outline of some of these system analysis techniques and where they came from.
Tanner, Bertrand: And then, as we get forward,
Tanner, Bertrand: we can start to go into some of the data fitting trials if you guys wanted to try to test some of that on your own, or I could…
Tanner, Bertrand: run the scripts for you, or Maddy could run the scripts for you, just to show you how they are, and talk about, like, some of the details of the data if we wanted to.
Tanner, Bertrand: So, I grew up in northern Utah.
Tanner, Bertrand: And… I went to University of Utah for my undergraduate, where I did a physics degree.
Tanner, Bertrand: And, I graduated from there in 2001.
Tanner, Bertrand: And then I worked for a company that did…
Tanner, Bertrand: biometorology or bioinstrumentation, where I was mostly designing carbon dioxide flux measurement equipment, so that was, like, in the early days of starting to measure
Tanner, Bertrand: greenhouse gases related to global warming, and I learned a lot on that job, but I really didn't like being told what to do all the time, or, like, not having some of the intellectual freedom of it, so I thought, oh, maybe I'll go back to graduate school, but I never really thought I'd…
Tanner, Bertrand: be a professor, I was just trying to get, like,
Tanner, Bertrand: a higher level degree to maybe have some more autonomy. And I did a PhD in bioengineering up in Seattle at University of Washington.
Tanner, Bertrand: And then I did a postdoc at University of Vermont in physiology and biophysics.
Tanner, Bertrand: And since 2013, I've been here at Washington State University, and I'm in the Department of
Tanner, Bertrand: Integrative Physiology and Neuroscience.
Tanner, Bertrand: And I've always very… since I started studying muscle, I've been very interested at how muscle couples these biophysical processes over different scales.
Tanner, Bertrand: Such as, you know, the molecular network of motors that allows force to be produced all the way up into much larger scale movement and locomotion, and it's…
Tanner, Bertrand: Just really interesting how that is organized, and how it works together to…
Tanner, Bertrand: Enable, a vast array of
Tanner, Bertrand: Different activities across the animal kingdom.
Tanner, Bertrand: And so, if we think about the contractile machinery of the heart, I think most of us all know this, but
Tanner, Bertrand: What we normally do is we take a piece of either the heart wall or the papillary muscle, and we pare it down into a small piece of tissue that's about 700 microns
Tanner, Bertrand: Long, or maybe a millimeter long, and about 200 microns wide.
Tanner, Bertrand: And, that's a multicellular preparation because, as you see here, this is a single cell, and so a single cell is much smaller than the dimensions I just told you about related to the myocardial strip, but this is what we attach to the
Tanner, Bertrand: rig, or the motor, where one side is attached to a force transducer, and the other side is attached to a motor. And so the striations are coming from the sarcomeres, where you get these
Tanner, Bertrand: thick and thin filaments. So thin filaments are shown in blue, and the thick filaments are shown in red, and then the proteins along them are
Tanner, Bertrand: You know, the contractile proteins actin and myosin, but then those are regulated by thin filament and thick filament regulatory proteins, such as troponin, which binds to calcium to allow actin and myosin to interact.
Tanner, Bertrand: And then there's the myosin light chains and myosin-binding protein C along the thick filament and on myosin. And the…
Tanner, Bertrand: proteins and the organization is very, very similar in skeletal muscle. There's a little bit of a difference in terms of how the innervation and activation happens, but this is, again, when we're doing skeletal tissue, it's a single fiber, and usually our single fibers, such as I've shown here,
Tanner, Bertrand: Our… we cut them down to somewhere around, like, 2 or 3 millimeters long, and the width of a single fiber kind of depends upon the muscle type and the animal that it comes from, but usually it's around maybe a diameter of 50 to 70.
Tanner, Bertrand: Microns across it.
Tanner, Bertrand: And it has very similar proteins as well.
Tanner, Bertrand: And so, some of the way that I think about, the processes that lead into force production is shown here on the bottom there, where we would see calcium binding to troponin, and then as
Tanner, Bertrand: That leads to tropomyosin moving to make these actin binding sites along the thin filament available for the crossbridge to bind, and as the cross bridge binds and produces force, that goes through this ATP-driven cross-bridge cycle that, enables muscle shortening and force production.
Tanner, Bertrand: And so I'm not going to talk today at all about the super relaxed state, although there is starting to become a whole different regulatory pathway along the thick filament that's been known about for a while, and there's a lot of study on this, and it's called the super-relaxed state, where the traditional calcium activation along the thin filament
Tanner, Bertrand: But there's something that might be, based on a force-sensitive or mechanotransduction regulatory pathway that augments these cross bridges laying down on the thick filament backbone versus popping up to be able to be involved with cross-bridge binding.
Tanner, Bertrand: So just to illustrate again.
Tanner, Bertrand: that process that I went through, we've got calcium binding, then you get exposing the thin filament binding sites, and when myosin binds to actin, it's in an ADP and phosphate state, so after it's hydrolyzed the ATP, it's got those nucleotide products.
Tanner, Bertrand: And then as it releases phosphate, that's when you get the power stroke that generates force, and then as ADP is released, ATP comes on, and that leads to dissociation.
Tanner, Bertrand: So… in… in…
Tanner, Bertrand: Also, in terms of what goes on with how muscle works, there's some changes in terms of…
Tanner, Bertrand: how the length and the tension, or the length and the stress or the force-length relationship are involved. And if you think about, passive and active changes with sarcomere length or muscle length.
Tanner, Bertrand: Here in green, you've shown, as you stretch out the sarcomere, at some point, you'll start to, even in the absence of any activation, you'll start to get an increase in the muscle force.
Tanner, Bertrand: Shown in green here, and that's the passive properties, which are largely driven by titan and collagen in the muscle.
Tanner, Bertrand: And then, if you think of just the active force, or the calcium-activated force, that's this blue line, which kind of goes up, hits the plateau, and then comes back down. And this is called the ascending limb.
Tanner, Bertrand: On the left, and on the right, it's the descending limb of the force-length relationship. And if you add those together, you get a total force.
Tanner, Bertrand: And in the back of my mind, I've been working over, sort of, the last decade wondering if this force-length relationship and what leads to force production is purely due to thin filament overlap, or if there might be some additional contributions that change
Tanner, Bertrand: with how the cross bridge goes through its cycle as you change the muscle length. And I've got one little example, we'll go over that today, but part of why I started thinking about this
Tanner, Bertrand: had to do with the Frank-Starling relationship, which that in the heart means if you get greater filling of the ventricle, the heart's gonna contract more forcefully and faster to eject more blood.
Tanner, Bertrand: As either your heart rate increases, or you get, just greater, greater filling, you need to match that greater ejection. And so.
Tanner, Bertrand: The Frank-Sarling law at the organ level suggests that cardiac output increases as that end diastolic volume, or that filling of the ventricle increases, and
Tanner, Bertrand: Normally, this is a relatively steep relationship, as shown in the black line, but the dashed line is… it's… this relationship is suppressed, and that occurs with disease or dysfunction and heart failure. And sort of at the molecular and cellular level.
Tanner, Bertrand: An analogous finding, or an analogous characteristic of muscle, is an increase in force and calcium sensitivity as you increase the muscle length. And so.
Tanner, Bertrand: If you think about force as a function of calcium, if you look at the log of calcium, as you increase calcium, you'll get an increase in force with this sigmoidal relationship, and that is greater maximum force and an increase in calcium sensitivity
Tanner, Bertrand: At the molecular and cellular level, like, we often measure force.
Tanner, Bertrand: And so… That's a bit of the background there.
Tanner, Bertrand: Does anybody have any questions before I go into any of the additional details of this one example of the sarcomere length from myocardial mechanics?
Tanner, Bertrand: Okay, so this next little example is looking at RAT myocardial mechanics, but this starts to get into some of the system analysis methods, where we're using, in this particular case, sinusoidal length perturbation analysis to probe the crossbridge kinetics.
Tanner, Bertrand: And so this is a system analysis method that is called single input, single output analysis, where the muscle acts as a viscoelastic system, and if you
Tanner, Bertrand: wiggle the muscle like you put a sinusoidal input into it by changing the length. That's going to have some sort of effect on the force or the stress, which is force per cross-sectional area for the system output.
Tanner, Bertrand: And so, if we think of strain as a function of time, shown here in black.
Tanner, Bertrand: You'll get some response for the stress, for the stress response as a function of time, and it's a… also a sine wave, because a lot of those system characteristics are preserved, but what's different is you get sort of some shift in time
Tanner, Bertrand: And this phase difference, or this shift in time between the input and the output, that changes as a function of frequency. So you'll get more or less shift in time as how this behaves. And that shift
Tanner, Bertrand: As a function of frequency, allows you to characterize or estimate some of what's going on with the cross-bridge cycling properties, or the cross-bridge kinetics.
Tanner, Bertrand: And so, the way we break this out is we turn this into an elastic and a viscous modulus. So the elastic component, when the muscle's acting like a spring, or the viscous component, when the muscle's acting like a damper.
Tanner, Bertrand: But you get a viscoelastic response as a summation of those in total.
Tanner, Bertrand: And so, you can break this up where the elastic response is directly in phase with the strain input, with the… this is the big dashed line, and that's some sort of elastic element, and then the amplitude related to the autophase component, or the…
Tanner, Bertrand: Sine wave would be… the… the viscous component.
Tanner, Bertrand: And so we can look at those characteristics and see how they change as a function of frequency to estimate cross-bridge cycling. And just to be…
Tanner, Bertrand: clear… the actual data that I'm showing you is coming from stochastic length perturbation analysis, where it's a sum of a bunch of sine waves, but that's just, like, a subtle detail. The principle is the same, it's just the data looks a little bit different.
Tanner, Bertrand: If you were actually looking at sinusoidal data versus, the Gaussian white noise data.
Tanner, Bertrand: So these are all in male rats.
Tanner, Bertrand: And we dissect and chemically skin the tissue.
Tanner, Bertrand: And then we bathe it in a solution bubble, the…
Tanner, Bertrand: we have activated the muscle to PCA4.8, so PCA is the negative log of the calcium concentration. So that's a high calcium concentration, and then we varied the ATP level because we were curious at estimating ATP release and ATP binding rates in the tissue.
Tanner, Bertrand: And so, the raw data looks something like this, where there's the elastic modulus on top, the viscous modulus on the bottom, and those are plotted against frequency.
Tanner, Bertrand: And so this is a log scale for the frequency, just to let you know. And the sarcomere length 2.2 microns, and sarcomere length 1.
Tanner, Bertrand: 9 microns, so in the longer sarcomere length is in black, and the shorter sarcomere length is in white. And you can see that you get sort of a similar response, but there's some shifts to it. And these shifts in the dips and the humps
Tanner, Bertrand: And how those change, vertically have to do with cross-bridge binding, and how those change horizontally have to do with the crossbridge kinetics.
Tanner, Bertrand: And so… We take these data and we fit it to a model.
Tanner, Bertrand: the model shown there in the top right corner that has to do with this A process that has to do with some of the passive characteristics of the tissue, and then this B and this C process have to do with cross-bridge dynamics, or cross-bridge cycling kinetics.
Tanner, Bertrand: And for the beginning of the talk here, I'm mostly just going to focus on this myosin detachment rate, which is this 2 pi C characteristic, which is inversely related to myosin attachment time.
Tanner, Bertrand: And so down here, I've tried to show, like, a unitary event of myosin-producing force as it goes through the crossbird cycle, and this is what we're calling myosin attachment time, when it's bound to actin. And there's different versions of… or there's different components of that nucleotide release that we're trying to probe.
Tanner, Bertrand: And so, if we think of how that myosin attachment time changes as a function of ATP, you see as you, like.
Tanner, Bertrand: start up here with saturating ATP at 5 millimolar ATP, and you decrease ATP down towards approximating Riger, or no ATP, which is the Riger state.
Tanner, Bertrand: You get a slowing of the CrossFit cycling, and you get an increase in this myosin attachment time.
Tanner, Bertrand: And so this is at sarcomere length 2.2, and so just if you were to imagine if we looked at an intermediate
Tanner, Bertrand: ATP level. You could imagine what's going on. The difference between this increase has to do with how long the crossbridge is waiting for ATP to bind. And so this can kind of break into two components.
Tanner, Bertrand: A linear combination of the time waiting for ADP to release, and a time waiting for ATP to bind. And if you assume that that ADP release rate is not affected by
Tanner, Bertrand: what's going on by changing ATP, then you can look at the overall time on being a sum of the two ATP release and ATP binding times, and you can estimate that to then get an ADP release rate and an ATP binding rate.
Tanner, Bertrand: And if you fit this data time on as a function of ATP, then you can pull out those characteristics at the bottom.
Tanner, Bertrand: And so then, if you look at the same data at starcomer length of 1.9, you can see that time on is decreased, but it's a very, very similar relationship. And if we fit that data, we saw that it looks like,
Tanner, Bertrand: the ADP release rate is…
Tanner, Bertrand: is much slower at the longer sarcomere length compared to the shorter sarcomere length. And even though there's a bit of a difference here, it wasn't significant, you'll notice that that ATP binding rate is much faster than the ADP release rate, and it turns out that in muscle fibers.
Tanner, Bertrand: The ADP release rate is the great limiting step of that cross-bridge detachment process, and so we think that this is a very important component of what regulates the kinetics, is the ADP release rate.
Tanner, Bertrand: And…
Tanner, Bertrand: So you could imagine, then, at the longer sarcomere length, you're also producing greater force, and so there's a clear correlation between being attached longer and generating more force, that there might be an underlying kinetic contribution to these changes in force as a function of sarcomere length.
Tanner, Bertrand: And so, I think one of the reasons this is, and this is sort of delving very much into the details of the biophysics, but I think the reason this might be happening is that as you're trying to go through that power stroke, or that cross bridge stroke.
Tanner, Bertrand: The ADP release is on the inside there of the head as you're trying to move that stroke, and it might be to get ADP to release somehow. If you're at a longer sarcomere length, or you're producing greater forces, you might be straining that cross bridge more.
Tanner, Bertrand: At the longer circum length, or with the greater force in the tissue.
Tanner, Bertrand: that changes how ADP comes out, and it might be a sort of a strain-dependent binding pocket component of the ADP release rate.
Tanner, Bertrand: So under, like, a high molecular strain at a longer sarcomere length, you might release ADP more slowly, and a lower molecular strain, you might release it faster. So that's just one idea.
Tanner, Bertrand: But sort of the take-home message from this…
Tanner, Bertrand: What we found from these data is that myosin cross-bridge kinetics flow as sarcomere length increases in the rat myocardial strips.
Tanner, Bertrand: And that might amplify cross-bridge contributions to thin filament activation and force production at longer circum lengths.
Tanner, Bertrand: And conversely, That might promote faster cross-bridge detachment and promote relaxation at shorter sarcomere lengths in the heart.
Tanner, Bertrand: And I think that might suggest link-dependent kinetics contribute in part to this Frank-Starling relationship.
Tanner, Bertrand: I also think there might be some sort of component of thinking about this overall force-length relationship.
Tanner, Bertrand: Where you've got a lot of what goes into it come from the changes in the thick and thin filament overlap as you change sarcomere length, but maybe there's some component of this that there's a cross-bridge contribution to the overall force-length relationship due to changes in myosin kinetics.
Tanner, Bertrand: So that's just one idea.
Tanner, Bertrand: And so we've done a lot of similar measurements in skeletal muscle as well, and a lot of these characteristics hold up in skeletal muscle, but it's not as obviously clear, or maybe not as big
Tanner, Bertrand: Of an effect in skeletal muscle as it is in cardiac muscle.
Tanner, Bertrand: So, a lot of this work has been supported by the National Finance Foundation and the American Heart Association, and some local grants I've gotten from my university.
Tanner, Bertrand: And, this is a good breaking point to take any questions if anybody has questions.
Tanner, Bertrand: Before we go further.
Victoria Wood: We have a question here in the chat, I can read over, Miles, if you want to unmute.
Tanner, Bertrand: I can try to pull up the chat, too.
Miles Valencia: It was just in that last slide where you were talking about the different sarcomere links and how that affected the ADP release rate. I know you, like, put up the model equation, but, like, when comparing the ADP release rate, did you take into account, like, the
Miles Valencia: difference in amount of ADP needed to produce the force? Because, like, I would assume… I would assume, well, the longer sarcomere lengths are going to require more ADP, or, like, have more cross bridges that would then release the ADP. So, I was just wondering if that was taken into account for the equations.
Tanner, Bertrand: The short answer is no. The… amount of ADP
Tanner, Bertrand: That is present in the system.
Tanner, Bertrand: is very, very low. We don't put any ADP in our solutions, and we have, ATP regenerating system.
Tanner, Bertrand: the creatine kinase that takes the released phosphate and ATP and recombines it to try to maintain your ATP levels where you've set them, and keep low ADP levels.
Tanner, Bertrand: So…
Tanner, Bertrand: In terms of the effects of ADP in the solution, or what might be going on at the different muscle lengths.
Tanner, Bertrand: I haven't ever thought much about that, because I was always assuming that we were just trying to have as little ADP as possible, and whatever goes on with the ADP release is coming from the myosin.
Tanner, Bertrand: hydrolyzing the ATP, and then it has phosphate and ADP bound.
Tanner, Bertrand: But there might be some characteristic, like you're trying to suggest that
Tanner, Bertrand: If you're bound for longer, or if you have more cross bridges bound at longer sarcomere lengths.
Tanner, Bertrand: Then there could be, sort of, some…
Tanner, Bertrand: Difference in the system of how the cross bridges might see the forces distributed throughout the sarcomere.
Tanner, Bertrand: But I hadn't thought about it in terms of, like, the biochemistry of the ADP changes.
Miles Valencia: Well, because my thought is, if the longer sarcomeres have more cross bridges, yet they're still releasing ADP at a slower rate, then, like.
Miles Valencia: Normalizing for size, it's actually… For whatever reason, it's… Yeah, it's, like, even more…
Miles Valencia: like, the ADP release rate is even lower than that. Or at least, that's my thought process of, like…
Miles Valencia: of it.
Miles Valencia: But, no, yeah, that was interesting. Thank you.
Tanner, Bertrand: Yeah, thanks for the question.
NAU watch party: I have a question.
NAU watch party: I don't know, maybe people do too. What do you think might explain the difference in the size of the effect between the cardiac and skeletal muscles?
Tanner, Bertrand: I think it has to do with the…
Tanner, Bertrand: Myosome isoform, and how the different myosin isoforms
Tanner, Bertrand: Either go through their crossbridge cycle, or how they might respond to, like, changes in the molecular strain.
Tanner, Bertrand: And I think…
Tanner, Bertrand: So, like, it seems to be a bigger relationship, or a large… like, the slow twitch muscle.
Tanner, Bertrand: Has a higher sensitivity, these changes in length, than the fast twitch.
Tanner, Bertrand: My essence?
Tanner, Bertrand: And I haven't done a lot of comparing across the different types of
Tanner, Bertrand: Cardiac myosins between the, like, alpha myosin, which is mostly in mice and rats, versus beta myosin, which is in bigger
Tanner, Bertrand: Animals, like anything bigger than a guinea pig, is primarily beta myosin, which is a slower myosin.
Tanner, Bertrand: The alpha myosin in mice and rat hearts is the fast isoformamyosin.
Tanner, Bertrand: But it might be a cardiac versus skeletal difference, or it might be a fast twitch versus slow twitch difference, because it's quite obvious that the slow twitch muscles
Tanner, Bertrand: Are much more sensitive to these changes in length than the length-dependent cross-bridge kinetics and the fast twitch muscles.
Tanner, Bertrand: The fast twitch myosins just don't seem to be nearly as affected by these changes in the muscle length.
Tanner, Bertrand: In terms of how they go through their cross-bridge kinetics. So their kinetics don't change with lengths very much by comparison to the slow twitch myosin.
NAU watch party: Yeah, that's really interesting. I didn't really know, because I'm kind of ignorant about cardiac muscle, that there is, like, fast and slow myosins in, cardiac, too, that depend on animal size, but that totally makes sense.
NAU watch party: Thanks, Barry.
Tanner, Bertrand: So, I… I don't have a great answer for that. I've been curious about, like, it would be really good if you could actually figure out and understand why
Tanner, Bertrand: or what is going on with all these different myosins, and when there's these sensitivities, and when there aren't, but I haven't been able to, like.
Tanner, Bertrand: Stitch it all together… yet.
Tanner, Bertrand: So, to kind of get into the second half of whatever we want to go over, or if we wanted to look at the data fitting, I wanted to just give a little bit of history on some of these system analysis methods, and where they came from, because anybody amongst us who's a bioengineer or an engineer
Tanner, Bertrand: Realizes that these are all the same
Tanner, Bertrand: Analysis methods that are often used in, like, signal processing, or often used in a whole bunch of, like, mechanical engineering
Tanner, Bertrand: applications, and so all of this stuff is, like, nothing new. It's just sort of a few people across the history of the muscle field have applied this to trying to understand some of the crossbridge
Tanner, Bertrand: Cycling kinetics.
Tanner, Bertrand: And so, as I had just mentioned earlier, this is the same slide, you know, there's a system input and a system output, and what goes on in between, there's mathematics that allow you to be able to
Tanner, Bertrand: look at whatever that transfer function is in the middle, and here it happens to be a viscoelastic system with muscle.
Tanner, Bertrand: And so this was just replaying this phase shift that changes as a function of that frequency.
Tanner, Bertrand: And how we've got the elastic and viscous modulus, if anybody was
Tanner, Bertrand: wanting to ask any questions while I follow up. This little model that we use, this ABC process model.
Tanner, Bertrand: primarily interprets Where these peaks are is associated largely with this myosin detachment rate, and where these dips are
Tanner, Bertrand: are largely associated with what we think of as the myosin attachment, or the crossbridge recruitment rate, and that comes from this, like, little B process, 2 pi B.
Tanner, Bertrand: So, we think of this as, like, a passive element of the tissue.
Tanner, Bertrand: that also has a viscoelastic characteristic, but then the cycling of the cross bridges with myosin attachment rates and myosin detachment rates in these B and C processes.
Tanner, Bertrand: And so, there was a paper from one of my postdoc advisors in 2007 that did a lot of theory work, but also a lot of computational modeling that tried to better understand these myosin detachment rates and how those were associated with
Tanner, Bertrand: the viscoelastic response. And so I wanted to go in and just introduce here… the raw data as a function of frequency is plotted on the left, but you can also make a Nyquist plot or a phase portrait of what's going on, where you
Tanner, Bertrand: Plot the elastic modulus, or the viscous modulus versus the elastic modulus, and that looks something like this, which gives you these… these loops, such as shown here.
Tanner, Bertrand: And that's that, again, that ABC model. Well, I think some of us know
Tanner, Bertrand: that you can characterize components of a system in the frequency domain or the time domain, and what links the frequency and time domain has to do with the Laplace transform.
Tanner, Bertrand: And so you can look at the frequency and time domain characteristics and identify similar processes or similar responses.
Tanner, Bertrand: And so, on the bottom right is an equation that is associated with the time domain representation of what would be in the frequency domain representation on the left.
Tanner, Bertrand: And this was sort of just an interesting thing to show you.
Tanner, Bertrand: For what goes on with a step stretch.
Tanner, Bertrand: Rather than a sinusoidal stretch. So the tension per strain is shown here on the right, where if you do a step stretch, like you just rapidly stretch the muscle, you'll get this sort of elastic increase
Tanner, Bertrand: to some peak.
Tanner, Bertrand: stress value, then you'll get this decay, and then it's relatively subtle here, but there's this recovery
Tanner, Bertrand: And then that sort of just goes out flat, depending on muscle type. It's either flat or it still kind of comes down to zero.
Tanner, Bertrand: But this fast phase is thought to be rapidly stretching the cross bridges, then phase two is this cross-bridge detachment, and then this recovery, or this phase three, is thought to maybe be cross-bridge binding or cross-bridge recruitment.
Tanner, Bertrand: And a lot of this came out, these phases of the Phase 1, 2, 3 stuff.
Tanner, Bertrand: All came out of some of the early
Tanner, Bertrand: Kinetic phases were developed in the late 1970s by…
Tanner, Bertrand: Andrew Huxley. And so, the first paper that tried to define all this was in 1977, but it's, like, an 80-page long paper that's relatively…
Tanner, Bertrand: that's relatively thorough in what they put forward, so most people haven't read this paper. The other paper that follows up with that a few years later.
Tanner, Bertrand: Or I guess this was even earlier, sorry, this is 1971. This was when they first looked at it. This is a very short paper that's often cited a lot, because it's only 2 or 3 pages long, and it kind of has the initial ideas of what these phases might be.
Tanner, Bertrand: But just to show you some of the raw data from that 1971 paper, what they started doing…
Tanner, Bertrand: On the top, you see strain as a function of time, and on the bottom, you see the force or the stress as a function of time.
Tanner, Bertrand: And so here you see they're trying to do this rapid step stretch.
Tanner, Bertrand: And it's zoomed in with so much in time that it kind of looks like a ramp, but this is very, very, very fast. Like, this is 2 milliseconds here, so this is a very fast stretch.
Tanner, Bertrand: And they were doing different stretch amplitudes, as well as stretch… or as well as shortening amplitudes. And so you see that you get a relatively symmetric response if you do this step stretch, and then as you shorten the amplitude.
Tanner, Bertrand: Or start to go to shortening, you kind of get the inverse, where instead of doing that fast up and then going down, you'd see this, like.
Tanner, Bertrand: rapid…
Tanner, Bertrand: decay in force, but then that recovery in force. And so, the symmetry of the stretching versus the shortening is what started to go into some of those ideas of what might be cross-bridge cycling and what these different phases might represent.
Tanner, Bertrand: And it was sort of…
Tanner, Bertrand: Out of this was this idea of where the crossbridge sort of started going through these multiple conformational changes, and what started to be defining a power stroke in more detail, was…
Tanner, Bertrand: Some ideas in this 1971 paper.
Tanner, Bertrand: Then, this is the 1980 paper that I uploaded, but I wanted to say that some of you in the audience who have studied muscle or studied insect muscle
Tanner, Bertrand: there was… Pringle did a whole bunch of this frequency-dependence
Tanner, Bertrand: analysis earlier than Kawhi and Brant did.
Tanner, Bertrand: Which is this sinusoidal analysis is a classic paper from 1980. And, they characterize things in terms of the, like, amplitude and the phase, so the dynamic modulus, and these are three different processes they're trying to define.
Tanner, Bertrand: And then how they change as a function of frequency. Just, like, to introduce you some of the…
Tanner, Bertrand: Ideas, but you can see, if you look at active data.
Tanner, Bertrand: As a function of frequency, this is plotting the stress and strain, and then the phase portrait of it, with how stress and strain would look within these loops.
Tanner, Bertrand: And you can see as you change your frequency, you get, like, different shapes and directions of this loop.
Tanner, Bertrand: And when you look at Riger, almost all of these different loops almost look the same.
Tanner, Bertrand: Because Ryder, you're having a much, much stiffer crossbridge.
Tanner, Bertrand: are much, much stiffer muscle, and the cross bridges aren't cycling. So, you can see there's obvious differences between the active muscle and the ragger muscle.
Tanner, Bertrand: And so that's just some of where this theory came from, I guess getting on towards 50 years ago now.
Tanner, Bertrand: And then I wanted to follow up with just showing you where some of the data comes from that we might be fitting today if we want to be doing the data fitting.
Tanner, Bertrand: And then,
Tanner, Bertrand: So what we do is we take a muscle, and we put it in this different bath of solution.
Tanner, Bertrand: And here I plotted the length and force as a function of time, and so we put it in this pre-activating solution, which is a solution that, has some different characteristics for how calcium is buffered.
Tanner, Bertrand: But it leads to faster activation, and therefore, like, less… Strain, or less.
Tanner, Bertrand: deterioration of the muscle. And then we switch it from the relaxing bath, now it's in the air during this component here, and then it goes into the activating calcium
Tanner, Bertrand: Bath, and you see that force develops as a function of time to some steady-state rate, and then we do that rapid length step.
Tanner, Bertrand: And, I've just listed the isometric force and stress there for this particular example.
Tanner, Bertrand: And if you look at two different muscle types, for example, and you zoom in on just the step stretch.
Tanner, Bertrand: And this is, subtracting off
Tanner, Bertrand: The stress before we do the stretch.
Tanner, Bertrand: And, you see that you'll get these responses.
Tanner, Bertrand: Where on the top is a fest twitch muscle with medial gastrocnemius from a rat.
Tanner, Bertrand: and you get this rapid stretch to some maximum, which we call T1, or Time 1 for the beginning of the Phase 1. Then that decays down to T2 for the beginning of the Phase 2. There's this, like, little recovery from T2 to T3,
Tanner, Bertrand: And then…
Tanner, Bertrand: You notice we're only looking here at 250 milliseconds for this example medial gastrocnemius fiber, so this is relatively quick, all this happens.
Tanner, Bertrand: you get a similar but different response for the soleus fiber, where, again, you've got these T1, T2, T3 components, but here we're looking over an entire second, so this is happening much, much slower in the soleus fiber.
Tanner, Bertrand: And the shapes of what's going on with these traces is a little bit different.
Tanner, Bertrand: These data fit really easily to,
Tanner, Bertrand: a dual exponential function, or you can look at, like, the half-time here as an estimate of how long it takes for the cross bridges to detach, or where you get this half-time between T1 and T2.
Tanner, Bertrand: You can do the same thing up here, but these data are much, much harder to fit with, like, a dual or triple exponential function, because everything's happening
Tanner, Bertrand: So fast for… All the different processes.
Tanner, Bertrand: Whereas, clearly, down here for the soleus fiber, you're getting a rapid detachment, and the detachment is much faster than, like, this recovery.
Tanner, Bertrand: Or this… ProsBridge recruitment or Attachment Phase 3 characteristic.
Tanner, Bertrand: And so… That is mostly what I've provided or brought together for the…
Tanner, Bertrand: stuff I was going to talk to you about, but as I mentioned, there's these data-fitting examples that Maddy Chastain had put together, and these all run with MATLAB, and this is what it looks like on my computer, which I can run stuff
Tanner, Bertrand: To give you guys examples above.
Tanner, Bertrand: Or this is what it looks like on the MC Google Drive, and if you click in the data fitting examples.
Tanner, Bertrand: There's these three different versions here, and within each of those folders, Maddy made a How to Use the Fitting Scripts PowerPoint, so that
Tanner, Bertrand: how to use the fitting script PowerPoint would sort of give you some introduction or what to expect.
Tanner, Bertrand: I've got this here for whenever we want to show this, Victoria, for people to… Scan things in.
Tanner, Bertrand: And I can also, you know, Maddy could show you how the data, or how the fitting scripts work on her computer, I could show you on my computer, or people could give it a try however they want.
Tanner, Bertrand: Does anybody have any feedback or desires on what to do next?
Victoria Wood: I think it'd be great if we could get a little bit of a demonstration from either you or Maddie.
Tanner, Bertrand: Okay.
Tanner, Bertrand: Maddy, do you want to do that?
Chastain, Maddy: Yeah, I can do it.
Tanner, Bertrand: And if your stuff isn't working for your soleus fitting, I have my stuff is working for soleus fitting.
Chastain, Maddy: Okay, awesome.
Chastain, Maddy: Go back there.
Chastain, Maddy: Let me share my screen.
Chastain, Maddy: Okay… Second…
Chastain, Maddy: They hear.
Chastain, Maddy: Can everyone see that?
Chastain, Maddy: my MATLAB.
Victoria Wood: Yes.
Chastain, Maddy: Awesome. Okay, so first, I'm gonna show the sinusoidal processing.
Chastain, Maddy: So, you just click run, Gonna change this folder here.
Chastain, Maddy: And then it kind of just goes for you. And so, in this graph here.
Chastain, Maddy: is the… the blue line is gonna be at PCA8, so that relaxed state.
Chastain, Maddy: And then the green line is gonna be at…
Chastain, Maddy: PCA4, I believe, and so that's gonna be when it's fully activated.
Chastain, Maddy: And so in the top graph is the elastic modulus, and then below is the viscous modulus, and these are both on a log scale of frequency.
Chastain, Maddy: And from these, we can gain the…
Chastain, Maddy: ABC parameters, and then the 2 pi and 2 pi B… parameters as well.
Chastain, Maddy: Little, and then…
Tanner, Bertrand: Do you want to show the output for just, like, it plots some of…
Tanner, Bertrand: So that's the individual plot, and then it also plots…
Chastain, Maddy: this one.
Tanner, Bertrand: So those are… The differences between the…
Tanner, Bertrand: The one on the run 1 versus Run 2 is the relaxed versus the activated.
Tanner, Bertrand: And both when you look at the raw data, but also when you try to fit it, you see there's quite different characteristics in terms of the relaxed data being a flat line, where you don't see any of those dips and humps, because the cross bridges aren't cycling, because the cross bridges aren't activated at the relaxed.
Tanner, Bertrand: fiber tissue, so you get what would be, like, just the passive viscoelastic response.
Chastain, Maddy: Yes.
Chastain, Maddy: So that's, like, why we see this straight line here.
Chastain, Maddy: Is what we're talking about.
Chastain, Maddy: Yeah, and then… So… Let me pull up the PowerPoint, too.
Chastain, Maddy: So, the, like, as Dr. Tanner was saying before, the elastic modulus shows the stiffness of the fiber in phase with the sinusoidal length change.
Chastain, Maddy: And this effect… reflects how strongly the cross bridges are attached, and then the viscous modulus, shows
Chastain, Maddy: The outer phase?
Chastain, Maddy: And this reflects the cross-bitch cycling, is kind of how I feel it as well.
Chastain, Maddy: Is there anything else?
Chastain, Maddy: You wanna add?
Tanner, Bertrand: I don't know, I think that's, like, a good… Start…
Tanner, Bertrand: The other sets of data that she put together were for the step analysis.
Tanner, Bertrand: And one of the reasons, while you're getting that pulled up, I can just tell Maddie, is one of the reasons
Tanner, Bertrand: There's advantages and disadvantages to the sinusoidal analysis versus the step analysis.
Tanner, Bertrand: But one of the disadvantages of the sinusoidal analysis is because you have to sweep over all those frequencies, is you have to keep the tissue activated for a long time, so you can get, decay or deterioration of the tissue.
Tanner, Bertrand: Or you can't activate it as many times. So, that's why, and more recently, we've been doing quite a bit of work trying to see if we can get the same information.
Tanner, Bertrand: Which, theoretically, you should be able to get the same information.
Tanner, Bertrand: From the, step analysis, because you can do, like, a rapid step stretch in really a fraction of the time
Tanner, Bertrand: You know, just a few seconds, compared to that sweep over time of, like, the sinusoids.
Tanner, Bertrand: Depending on your frequency range, or how fast your muscle is, or what temperature you're working at, sometimes it can be, like, a minute and a half, or two minutes to get over all those frequencies.
Tanner, Bertrand: Especially if you have, like,
Tanner, Bertrand: Slower myosin, where you need to do lower frequency
Tanner, Bertrand: Lower frequency stimulus, your strain input.
Tanner, Bertrand: So there's… there's a lot of little caveats to what works and what doesn't work, depending on how you're running your experiment. Like, I'm sure all of you guys
Tanner, Bertrand: Know and battle with every day, trying to do the best measurements you can without
Tanner, Bertrand: Having your tissue deteriorate on you.
Chastain, Maddy: Yeah, yeah, and so this is the step analysis. So, how this works… so it's gonna be different for Mac and Windows, because the crosshair, function doesn't work on Mac computers, so there's two different versions of the code, one for Windows and one for Mac.
Chastain, Maddy: There. And so, basically, you're gonna click on the rising force here between the two, which is down at this bottom point.
Chastain, Maddy: And then the 3 will be somewhere over here, and so that's to help calculate the T3.
Chastain, Maddy: So, let's see if it works. And then you'll get a graph like that.
Chastain, Maddy: And we'll have me do it again.
Chastain, Maddy: Until I run through all of them.
Tanner, Bertrand: And so what she's doing over and over and over again here is we did a whole bunch of steps at different ATP levels.
Tanner, Bertrand: And I can come back and explain what's going on with the different,
Tanner, Bertrand: Figures that are, like, all popping up here, but if she goes through and does all this, you'll see the entire result, but…
Tanner, Bertrand: We were trying to recreate some of those
Tanner, Bertrand: plots that are equivalent to the myosin detachment rate as a function of ATP.
Tanner, Bertrand: or the myosin time on as a function of ATP.
Tanner, Bertrand: And so we changed the A…
Tanner, Bertrand: TP levels, like titrating them towards Riger, and you can see now that that curve
Tanner, Bertrand: It's starting to change, or, like, the detachment rate and the recruitment rate are starting to slow down.
Tanner, Bertrand: as she's getting to lower and lower ATP levels, and ultimately.
Tanner, Bertrand: as you get to the lowest ATP levels, sort of those dips in the curve totally decay, and it turns into something
Tanner, Bertrand: Or, I mean, they go away, and it turns into something that some of you might look at and say, oh, that looks much more like a passive response.
Chastain, Maddy: -Oh.
Chastain, Maddy: I think my…
Tanner, Bertrand: Are you still going, or did it stop?
Chastain, Maddy: Later is malfunctioning.
Chastain, Maddy: Oh no, it stopped. Wait, no, it's still gone. I think it's my computer, it's running too many things, but…
Chastain, Maddy: Let me post some things.
Tanner, Bertrand: Because I've…
Chastain, Maddy: Okay, let's see if it keeps running. Has it just… Malfunctioned.
Tanner, Bertrand: Because I can run it to a few… are having trouble.
Chastain, Maddy: Yeah…
Chastain, Maddy: I don't know what's happening… I'm so…
Tanner, Bertrand: Okay.
Chastain, Maddy: Okay.
Tanner, Bertrand: So, if you want to stop sharing for a second, I can try to do it.
Chastain, Maddy: Yeah.
Chastain, Maddy: Okay.
Tanner, Bertrand: So… I'll just run… One of these steps, for example, for right now.
Tanner, Bertrand: And these are these little crosshairs that maybe Max, it doesn't work with, but the reason we were doing this is trying to find
Tanner, Bertrand: Trying to tell the computer better on where the, like.
Tanner, Bertrand: T2 versus T3 transition might be.
Tanner, Bertrand: And…
Tanner, Bertrand: it goes through and it takes all this, and it tries to find, you know, this T1, T2, T3 stuff to keep track of those phases, but I also tried to do some things where I was fitting these data
Tanner, Bertrand: to a dual exponential fit, and you see this doesn't work very well with just a dual exponential fit without sort of some offset. So this here is a dual exponential fit with an offset, and it works a little better.
Tanner, Bertrand: And then over here in the bottom right.
Tanner, Bertrand: Is that… that step fit to that ABC process?
Tanner, Bertrand: So, we do a lot of things trying to see what works best, and what is more reliable, and what represents the kinetics.
Tanner, Bertrand: And sometimes it works out really cleanly, and other times it's a little trickier. But that's what this pops up for every single
Tanner, Bertrand: One that you want to fit?
Tanner, Bertrand: And then, like, if you were to just uncomment a few of these, this is the whole titration.
Tanner, Bertrand: And even if I just run a couple of them, so we don't have to run as many.
Tanner, Bertrand: Like, it'll make a curve and try to do that fitting to the…
Tanner, Bertrand: to that, ADP and ADP release and ATP binding.
Tanner, Bertrand: Equation to try to just estimate some of those rates.
Tanner, Bertrand: And so you see how these curves are starting to change a little bit.
Tanner, Bertrand: As we get to less and less… ATP.
Tanner, Bertrand: And, like, this is getting down towards the very end.
Tanner, Bertrand: And you see that this is starting to look much more like a passive response. And so, on top is the strain, and on the bottom is the step stress. And this shows you, sort of.
Tanner, Bertrand: If you look at the change and all this dip starts to slow, or this dip shifts to the right and then goes away, that's what's happening as you're getting less and less ATP, or the cross bridges are staying attached longer, waiting for ATP to bind.
Tanner, Bertrand: And then, this at the bottom.
Tanner, Bertrand: because this is a rate, not an attachment time, so it's the inverse of the attachment time I showed you in the previous PowerPoint, but…
Tanner, Bertrand: This is a fit to that function to get an ADP release rate and an ATP binding rate.
Tanner, Bertrand: Just as an example.
Tanner, Bertrand: So that's,
Tanner, Bertrand: That's one of the things that…
Tanner, Bertrand: She put forward to show you guys, and then this is… Just if we wanted to…
Tanner, Bertrand: fit some of the data that was the SOLEAS data.
Tanner, Bertrand: For the skeletal muscle?
Tanner, Bertrand: And this is fitting a few different Traces?
Tanner, Bertrand: In total, it's, like, two traces from two different muscle fibers.
Tanner, Bertrand: Where we changed the muscle length a little bit.
Tanner, Bertrand: And this is sort of the summary plot, if you're looking at… on top is sarcomere length 2.4, and our bottom is sarcomere length 2.7.
Tanner, Bertrand: And there's two traces for each of them. And then on the right, this is just the stress normalized to this peak stress.
Tanner, Bertrand: So we were just kind of looking at the data a few different ways.
Tanner, Bertrand: But again, for each fiber, That'll fit.
Tanner, Bertrand: your, like, T1, T2, T3 stuff?
Tanner, Bertrand: And then I also fit this to a dual exponential with an offset, and we tried to do this ABC process fitting, and so you see that clearly this dual exponential with an offset looks and fits really nicely, but this ABC model doesn't fit nearly as nicely.
Tanner, Bertrand: So, these are all sort of things that are a work in progress.
Tanner, Bertrand: And then, I don't know, Maddy, are you ready to show the fast twitch step stuff?
Tanner, Bertrand: Or do you want me to show it while I have it all up here?
Chastain, Maddy: Yeah. My MATLAB froze.
Tanner, Bertrand: Okay.
Tanner, Bertrand: So this is… The same thing, except this is through that medial gastroc data.
Tanner, Bertrand: So this is a fast twitch.
Tanner, Bertrand: Skeletal muscle.
Tanner, Bertrand: And it essentially does the same thing.
Tanner, Bertrand: Except we tried to do some data fitting differently, and some of it's working, and some of it's not working.
Tanner, Bertrand: But here you see, for these particular traces, There seems to be…
Tanner, Bertrand: Much more difference than what's going on.
Tanner, Bertrand: And also, this sort of recovery recruitment event being different in the orange versus the blue.
Tanner, Bertrand: And so, you know, this is sort of a piecewise fit, the pulling apart and doing a bunch of single exponential fits to different parts of this, which I don't think is a good idea, but I was trying to see what fit and didn't fit.
Tanner, Bertrand: This is that dual exponential fit, which it does really good for the first part of the curve, but doesn't do very well for the overall curve.
Tanner, Bertrand: And so, these are just some example
Tanner, Bertrand: code and example data that Maddy put together that we could share with everybody.
Tanner, Bertrand: But those are the four different examples there, and if I were to…
Tanner, Bertrand: You know, go in here and look at what's in here for the data fitting stuff.
Tanner, Bertrand: You know, there's these 3 different folders.
Tanner, Bertrand: And so, you know, As an example, for the sinusoidal stuff, there's this PowerPoint.
Tanner, Bertrand: Which, you sort of…
Tanner, Bertrand: Started to bring that forward and says, you know, run this script, and then this is what you'd expect to get, and she tried to write what the data means to try to help coordinate or illustrate what comes out.
Tanner, Bertrand: So, just to sort of…
Tanner, Bertrand: Let you guys know on what you're dealing with, or what we put forward there.
Tanner, Bertrand: That's an example of what we have.
Tanner, Bertrand: So, I don't know if, do you want me to put the slide back up for people's attendance?
Tanner, Bertrand: Victoria?
Victoria Wood: Yeah, yeah, go ahead.
Victoria Wood: That'll be helpful.
Tanner, Bertrand: Is that big enough for everyone?
Victoria Wood: Yeah, that should work.
Victoria Wood: I think Kisa has a question.
Tanner, Bertrand: Sure.
NAU watch party: Hey, Bert, so…
NAU watch party: How do you fit the… so you have, like, the ABC, and the A is the passive.
NAU watch party: And I'm just wondering, like, how you fit the passive…
NAU watch party: and maybe… maybe that's a question about, like, how you fit all the parameters, but, yeah, I'm just wondering how you estimate, like, the… the passive component of the…
NAU watch party: Sort of viscoel elastic behavior.
NAU watch party: In your data. Does that make sense?
Tanner, Bertrand: Yeah, I'm trying to think of how to best answer that.
Tanner, Bertrand: Did this PowerPoint, or does this paper pop up? You guys are seeing the paper?
NAU watch party: Yeah.
Tanner, Bertrand: I don't know where the…
Tanner, Bertrand: When I put it to share with you, the figure goes away.
Tanner, Bertrand: What the heck?
NAU watch party: That is really weird.
Tanner, Bertrand: So there, it's back now.
Tanner, Bertrand: So… These shapes, whether it's in the frequency or whether it's in the time domain, come from…
Tanner, Bertrand: Different shapes that you can… Look at as a summation of what these equations are.
Tanner, Bertrand: And when you break this down into the shapes of…
Tanner, Bertrand: What the viscous and elastic modulus look like.
Tanner, Bertrand: Unless you study these a lot, it's a little confusing, and these aren't very helpful.
Tanner, Bertrand: But… If you've looked at these a lot.
Tanner, Bertrand: There's different characteristics of vistoelastic behavior that fit into these different quadrants.
Tanner, Bertrand: In the frequency domain, and then there's different components of that same thing.
Tanner, Bertrand: Whether you're, like, a downward step with a recovery, or an upward step with a detachment, or the passive is shown here.
Tanner, Bertrand: And the dashed line, which is just up, and then it decays.
Tanner, Bertrand: And so the amplitude of where this Trace ends up…
Tanner, Bertrand: That amplitude of that is what is this A?
Tanner, Bertrand: And then…
Tanner, Bertrand: The slope of how fast it gets there, or the characteristic of how it approaches there, is a balance between the viscous and the elastic component of the elastic and visc… the visceral elastic response and the passive.
Tanner, Bertrand: And that slope… I mean, you could calculate it directly if you wanted to look at just one second, because at one second.
Tanner, Bertrand: you got A to the negative K, which makes the Ka the slope at time equals 1, but it basically has to do with what is this amplitude
Tanner, Bertrand: And then, how steep… Or how fast it gets into that.
Tanner, Bertrand: final amplitude.
NAU watch party: Yeah, okay, I mostly get that.
NAU watch party: So… and I just have another question, and I realize this is kind of a picky question, but I noticed this in your PowerPoint, and I also noticed it here, and I'm wondering, like, how come the viscous modulus doesn't have…
NAU watch party: Units of newton seconds per meter.
NAU watch party: Squared.
NAU watch party: Is that just, like… Yeah.
NAU watch party: Typo, or…
Tanner, Bertrand: No.
Tanner, Bertrand: So this is the stress divided by the strain.
Tanner, Bertrand: And this down here is the…
Tanner, Bertrand: stress divided by the strain as well, but I know that's not answering your question, but why would…
NAU watch party: So, like, the units of… like, the units of… Viscosity are newton seconds per…
NAU watch party: Anyway, I'll work it out for myself. That was a picky question.
Tanner, Bertrand: These are just amplitudes.
NAU watch party: Yeah, don't… I'll work it out, and I'll ask you later.
Tanner, Bertrand: Okay, well… I don't think these are typos. If they're typos, they've been typos for 20 years.
Tanner, Bertrand: Which wouldn't be very good.
Tanner, Bertrand: So I… yeah.
Tanner, Bertrand: Does anybody else have any questions? Are there any things to go over?
Victoria Wood: One thing, if people are still thinking of questions, I know you uploaded a lot of literature into that folder, do you mind kind of stepping through the ones that you
Victoria Wood: Recommend for different topics and things, just so that people know how to navigate that.
Tanner, Bertrand: Well… I mean, I don't think any of them are, like, critical to…
Tanner, Bertrand: anything I talked about today, but I wanted to make sure, like, the resources were there from some of the pictures and images I showed.
Tanner, Bertrand: So, like, these two were from…
Tanner, Bertrand: trying to define those, like, step stretch phase one, phase two, phase three, phase four ideas.
Tanner, Bertrand: Are the top two.
Tanner, Bertrand: And then that one that I did with the sinusoidal analysis that I showed you.
Tanner, Bertrand: That's this Kawhi and Brandt one.
Tanner, Bertrand: And then that Palmer one was what I was talking about with the detachment rates, and where some of the theory came from.
Tanner, Bertrand: Related to,
Tanner, Bertrand: Related to the ATP titration idea?
Tanner, Bertrand: And then, these…
Tanner, Bertrand: Don't have anything that I showed you today, aside from this one compares sinusidal analysis to white noise analysis.
Tanner, Bertrand: And this bottom one does a lot of comparison between sinusoidal analysis and step analysis.
Tanner, Bertrand: So these are just, like, very basic…
Tanner, Bertrand: background papers that I just wanted to make sure
Tanner, Bertrand: Were there so people didn't have to go looking for them if they wanted to read them at all.
Victoria Wood: Perfect. Thanks. That's helpful to have there.
Chastain, Maddy: If I would recommend
Chastain, Maddy: two of the papers that he put there that helped me understand it. I think the Huxley and Simmons 1970
Chastain, Maddy: 1971, if you want to read the short one.
Chastain, Maddy: Which I did. And then the Kawhi and Brandt 1980, those were the most helpful for me to understand both this stuff and sinusoidal analysis, and what each part of the equations meant, and how they apply to
Chastain, Maddy: The different parts of the analysis through the,
Chastain, Maddy: Through the code and everything that we ran.
Tanner, Bertrand: Well, thanks for sharing with that, Maddie. That's good to know. I'm sure that would help.
Victoria Wood: Alright, any other questions online? If… I know with some of our watch parties, it's hard to unmute, necessarily. If you…
Victoria Wood: Want to put them in the Slack as well? Feel free, I can monitor the Slack.
Victoria Wood: But otherwise, I guess, is, if that's all you have for today, we can go ahead and let people out a little bit early if you're willing to stay on for a few minutes and answer any additional questions people have before they head out. I think that'd be helpful, but…
Tanner, Bertrand: Okay.
Miles Valencia: Thank you!
Tanner, Bertrand: No worries, thank you.
Tanner, Bertrand: You guys have a good day, good luck with your science!
NAU watch party: Thanks, Bert and Maddy. I have a lot of questions for you guys, but I'll talk to you in person.
Tanner, Bertrand: Okay, that sounds good. Thanks, Keystone.
NAU watch party: Yeah, yeah, we'll see you guys tomorrow.
Tanner, Bertrand: Okay, cool.
NAU watch party: Bye.
Victoria Wood: Alright, awesome. I guess there weren't any other questions. So thank you guys.
Tanner, Bertrand: Yeah, thanks for all your help with everything, Victoria.
Victoria Wood: Yeah, yeah, of course. Oh, one quick thing I did want to go over, so,
Victoria Wood: we got the subaward materials, I'll input all of that today, and hopefully we can actually get the ball rolling there. But,
Victoria Wood: I wanted to touch base on Maddie's travel plans while she's here, too, for Capstone Symposium. I want to make sure we can fund her if necessary. You and I can talk about this offline, Bert.
Victoria Wood: If that's more helpful, but which… whichever funding mechanism works best, we can talk about that, but Maddie, we'd love to have you at UC Irvine in person. Yeah.
Chastain, Maddy: Yeah.
Tanner, Bertrand: Like, I think… It's totally…
Tanner, Bertrand: Trying to do her on the subaward with her travel on the subaward, if… It gets through… In time.
Victoria Wood: Yeah.
Tanner, Bertrand: And I guess if it doesn't, then…
Victoria Wood: Then we'll be ready.
Tanner, Bertrand: I have to go the other way, but…
Victoria Wood: Damn.
Tanner, Bertrand: I think the way we were planning on that sounds just fine to me.
Victoria Wood: Okay.
Tanner, Bertrand: I don't know what goes on with,
Tanner, Bertrand: how all this stuff has to process, and I know you guys have been…
Tanner, Bertrand: Having to deal with a whole bunch with how, you know, long the money's been getting delayed the last couple years and things like that, so…
Tanner, Bertrand: We're pretty flexible to just try to do whatever we can to help out and make things work.
Victoria Wood: I appreciate that. Thanks for your patience. Yeah, there… we might have to just be a little bit flexible at the time of the capstone Symposium with where the reimbursement gets processed in that case, but, please do plan on coming, and we'll make sure, one way or another, it gets reimbursed.
Tanner, Bertrand: Okay.
Chastain, Maddy: Bye, awesome.
Tanner, Bertrand: Sounds good.
Victoria Wood: Cool.
Victoria Wood: Alright.
Tanner, Bertrand: Alright, thank you.
Victoria Wood: Thank you.
Chastain, Maddy: Aye.
Tanner, Bertrand: Bye.
Victoria Wood: Right.